{
  "reference_number": "10190",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The government must first acknowledge that reductions alone will not reduce atmospheric levels of CO2. The goal must be to\n produce negative net GHG emissions as soon as absolutely possible. And secondly acknowledge that our addiction to energy\n\n consumption will need to be addressed in a manner similar to the US's War on Drugs and “Homeland Security” .it is entirely\n appropriate to consider deployment of the NZDF to prevent devastation to the economy and stability of New Zealand through\n mitigation and restoration approaches.This would be consistent with the three defence policy objectives: to defend New Zealand\n\n against low-level threats; to contribute to regional security; and to play a part in global security efforts.[ Increasing GHGs is a slow but\n extremely high level threat]."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Reductions are insufficient. There must be sequestrations. Neither technical sequestration of produced CO2, nor reduction in the\n combustion of fossil fuels is capable of reducing atmospheric CO2 levels. Plants do it as they grow. A sustainable portion of the\n\n developed biomass can be converted to metabolically inert carbon, as chars, and returned, beneficially to soils."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "With the exception that in the event that budgeted targets are met in advance, then the targets for the subsequent phase should be\n advanced."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The limited abilities of economic systems to adapt rapidly requires that they have a sense of some timely security. There will be\n strains, and pains, as the current systems must adapt to the realities that are being and will be experienced."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "\"Should not be changed\" unless targets are met sooner and changes are to accelerate the subsequent phase and goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The conditions that are being created by the economic system are \"exceptional circumstances\". The inherited conventions of social\nresponses by governments and commercial interests have been to revert to deferral of change to the practices which have\n\nprecipitated the contemporary exceptional circumstances. Deferrals must not be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With the Commission as a \"decision-maker\".. the Government should have the capacity to set aside the decisions by parliamentary\n\naction without causing damage to the Commission's stability and continuing functions.."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1). For all members of Government to become aware of the eminent dangers of anthropologically induced climate change to the\neconomy and social stability.– A legislated insistence that participants in government actions become educated, to the extent of their\n\nabilities, in the best available information and projections that science can provide.. 2) Establish means to meet the budgets with\nlogistical and strategic effectiveness such as may be provided by the NZDF. (The effort may well require \"military\" interventions to\n\nassure proactive actions, and rapid response to unanticipated events)."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Commission should present decisions and positions based on their monitoring of progress and developing knowledge. If\nGovernment chooses.to ignore those decisions.. leave it to the people."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Te Climate Change Commission needs only individuals with expertise related to changes related to climate, as they have occurred,\nare occurring and are projected to occur. The issues of social and economic stability should remain within the purview of elected\nGovernments."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The adaptations, as actions taken in reaction to events, are unrelated to establishing net zero (or negative) carbon dioxide (and other\nGHGs) emissions.The Zero Carbon Bill should remain proactive, laying the foundations for preemptive and protective action to reduce\n\nconsequences of projected climate changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "..Not entirely..-from ZeroCarbon Bill , Discussion Document,p.47.. \"At the moment, the way we respond and adapt to climate change\n\nimpacts is not well coordinated. Many of the risks, impacts and actions to adapt are dealt with across a number of different legislative\nand regulatory regimes.\" --Would not the NZDF provide either the agency or the model to follow?"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And.. make the reports easily accessible and published for observation by all organisations and the public.."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I greatly respect the hundreds, or thousands, of hours devoted to these efforts. But one aspect of 'adaptation' has not been\nmentioned, and it may be as dangerous as continued GHG emissions. The process of reaching action is heavily front-end loaded,\n\nburdened, by the time and expense it seems to take before any action emerges. The established political process is wasteful,\ndestructive of time and intellectual power that could be applied to a diversification of approaches that fit needed local individuals and\n\ncultural adaptions.. Freeing adaptation from preconceived concepts and politically derived national compliances may be required.."
    }
  ]
}
